Finding Aid for Albert B. Cleage Jr. papers, 1949-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Albert B. Cleage Jr. papers 1949-2005
Cleage, Albert B.
11.5 linear feet
2010025 Aa 2
Detroit clergyman who took the name Jaramogi Abebe Agyeman, founder of the Shrine of the Black Madonna, and advocate of the program and philosophy of the Black Christian Nationalist movement. The collection has been divided into four series: Albert B. Cleage, Jr.: Correspondence, Sermons, and Writings, the files of the Shrine of the Black Madonna in Detroit, Michigan, Church Leaders, and the files of the Shrine of the Black Madonna National Office.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was made available for microfilming by Kristin Cleage Williams and the Shrine of the Black Madonna National Office (donor no. 9897 ) in June 2007. The original papers were donated to the Bentley Historical Library in 2010.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
A substantial portion of the Cleage papers have been microfilmed. See the finding aid for Albert B. Cleage, Jr. papers [microform].
The oldest son of Dr. Albert B. Cleage, Sr. and Mrs. Pearl Cleage, Albert B. Cleage, Jr. was born June 13, 1911 in Indianapolis, Indiana. He grew up in Detroit, where his father had migrated to become the first Black city physician.
A graduate of Northwestern High School, Cleage attended Fisk University for a year before receiving his bachelor's degree from Wayne State University. He earned the equivalent of a doctoral degree from Oberlin's Graduate School of Theology in 1943, and did post-doctoral studies at the University of California. Before entering the seminary, Cleage was a social case worker with the Detroit Department of Public Welfare. With his divinity degree, Cleage led congregations in Lexington, Ken.; San Francisco, Cal.; and Springfield, Mass. before returning to Detroit in 1951 to become pastor at St. Mark's Presbyterian Church.
At St. Mark's, Cleage became concerned about the church's role in community affairs and the social issues of the time. In dispute with his denomination, Cleage left the church in 1953 taking with him 300 members who would become the core for a new church, St. Mark's Congregational Church. In 1954, St. Mark's would become Central Congregational Church.
Until 1954, Cleage and his parishioners held services at the Crossman School, but with a growing congregation he negotiated purchase of a mansion at 2254 Chicago Blvd. which would serve both as a parsonage and place to hold all church activities. The Church soon outgrew this location and the need to secure a large church became a major concern of the membership. The Brewster-Pilgrim Church located at 7625 Linwood was purchased in June 1957 with occupancy taking place in September of the same year.
As the Congregation grew, the membership under Cleage's leadership became increasingly involved in problems touching the lives of the African American community. Emphasis was placed on political involvement which was nurtured through the publication, beginning in 1960, of the Illustrated News, a newspaper devoted to the issues confronting the black community.
From the pulpit, Cleage began preaching sermons calling for the creation of a new black theology, and a new Black church to articulate that theology. Between 1967 and 1970 the church began restructuring the rituals, programs and structures of the traditional black church to conform to the Black Christian Nationalist philosophy. The name of Central Congregational Church was officially changed to the Shrine of the Black Madonna in 1970 by which time the first book written by Rev. Cleage was released. The Black Messiah published in 1968 was a series of powerful sermons introducing to the world a new Black theology. In 1972 Rev. Cleage published his second book, Black Christian Nationalism: New Direction for the Black Church. This book presented the complete program, position and philosophy of the black Christian Nationalist Movement. Around this same time, Cleage and other members began taking African names to distinguish themselves from the names given to them as slaves in bondage. Cleage would become Jaramogi Abebe Agyeman.
The decade of the 70's was a time of rapid expansion of the Shrines of the Black Madonna. Early in 1974 a small College Cadre of young men and women moved to Atlanta, Georgia to enroll in Atlanta University and to begin the organization of a shrine. The following year in April fifteen buses and many cars transported hundreds of members to Atlanta for the BCN Convention marking the opening of Shrine Nine and the Southern Regional Office.
In 1977 the next expansion cadre opened Shrine Seven taking the BCN Program to Kalamazoo, Michigan. In that same year, selected men and women from Shrine One in Detroit and Shrine Nine in Atlanta agreed to go to Houston, Texas to open and operate what would become Shrine Ten and the New Southwest Regional Offices and Training Center. The first Pan-American Synod was held in Houston, Texas in 1978 and it here that the Shrine of the Black Madonna was established as a new denomination and adopting the name Pan-African Orthodox Christian Church. Over the next two decades, under Cleage's leadership, the denomination would hold conventions of the Synod and annual leadership conclaves, the purpose of which was to bring together the different geographic shrines for discussion of the church's theology and programs.
The 1980s and 1990s saw continued growth and the development of new programs. In 1981, began raising funds to purchase farmland in South Carolina to be used to develop a network of independent Black farms and which could also be used for youth and adult retreats and training. In 1999, 2600 acres of land was purchased in Abbeville County, South Carolina. The property was known as the Beulah Land Farm. Members from Detroit and elsewhere made decision to relocate there. Among them was Jaramogi Abebe Agyeman.
In his life, Albert Cleage / Jaramogi Abebe Agyeman was married, had two daughters, and later divorced. He died at Beulah Land Farm on February 20, 2000.
The collection contains correspondence, sermons, and writings of Albert B. Cleage, Jr. (his name would later be changed to Jaramogi Abebe Agyeman); records of the shrine of the Black Madonna; papers of individuals within the church who assisted Cleage; and records of the National Office of the Shrine.
The collection has been divided into seven series: Albert B. Cleage, Jr.: Correspondence, Sermons, and Writings, the files of the Shrine of the Black Madonna in Detroit, Michigan, Church Leaders, the files of the Shrine of the Black Madonna National Office, Sound Recordings, Photographs, and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
African American clergy--Michigan--Detroit.; African Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; African Americans--Race identity.; Black nationalism--United States.; Black theology.; Central Congregational Church (Detroit, Mich.); Cleage, Albert B.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Jesus Christ--African American interpretations.; Pan African Orthodox Christian Church.; Race relations--Religious aspects--Christianity--United States.; Shrine of the Black Madonna (Detroit, Mich.); St. Mark's Congregational Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Albert B. Cleage, Jr.: Correspondence, Biographical, Sermons, and Writings
  The Albert B. Cleage, Jr.: Correspondence, Biographical, Sermons, and Writings series documents Cleage importance as a clergyman and as a leader locally within Detroit's African American community and nationally as a spokesman for Black pride. The correspondence file spans the years 1954 to 1978 and details Cleage's interactions with both religious and civil rights leaders across the country, as well as within Detroit. This series also includes sermons from the early 1950's through 1983, giving a detailed look at Cleage's views and thoughts. Finally, there are manuscripts of Cleage's two books Black Messiah and Black Christian Nationalism, along with a third, unpublished work, Nothing Is More Sacred Than the Liberation of the Black People.
  - Correspondence
    - 1954-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1962 (Box 1)
    - 1963 (Box 1)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - 1966 (Box 1)
    - 1967 (Box 1)
    - 1968, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1969, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1970 (Box 1)
    - 1971 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1977 (Box 1)
    - 1978 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Biographical, political, early career
    - Biographical Data 1969 (Box 1)
    - Memorials, obituaries, tributes to Jaramogi Abebe Agyeman February 2000 (Box 1)
    - Articles about Cleage and his church 1950-2004 (Box 1)
    - Detroit Board of Education candidacy 1966 (Box 1)
    - Detroit City Council candidacy 1965 (Box 1)
    - Congressional candidacy 1966 (Box 1)
    - Cartoon with image of Cleague confronting a Detroit businessman/politician undated (Box 1)
    - St John's Congregational Church, Springfield, Massachusetts 1949-1950 (Box 1)
  - Sermons (mimeographed)
    - 1970
      - Harlem Message August 11, 1970 (Box 1)
    - 1977
      - Two Worlds August 4, 1977 (Box 1)
      - Two Worlds August 11, 1977 (Box 1)
      - A New Heaven and a New Earth December 11, 1977 (Box 1)
      - End of an Era: We Are the Messianic Hope of the Twentieth Century December 25, 1977 (Box 1)
    - 1978
      - A New Era: January 8, 1978 (Box 1)
      - New Church for a New Era January 15, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Acting for God January 22, 1978 (Box 1)
      - The Community of Jesus...Today's Messianic Hope January 29, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Fruits of the Spirit February 5, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Sign of Jonah in This Day February 12, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Fragmentary April 2, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Discipline: Second in Series May 14, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Discipline: Third in Series May 21, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Prelude to a New Era: Between God and the Devil June 23, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Prelude to a New Era: The New Fantasy June 25, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Prelude to a New Era: No Options: Third in Series July 2, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Prelude to a New Era: Discipline: Fourth in Series July 9, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Prelude to a New Era: KUA: Fifth in Series July 16, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Climbing Jacob's Ladder August 13, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Theology of the Group Experience September 24, 1978 (Box 1)
      - The Revolutionary Mysticism of Jesus October 1, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Anniversary Month October 22, 1978 (Box 1)
      - The Church as a Transforming Community: Conversion #2 November 5, 1978 (Box 1)
      - The Church as a Transforming Community: Response to the Holy Spirit November 12, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Christianity and the Consciousness Revolution November 19, 1978 (Box 1)
    - 1979
      - The Black Dilemma: Drifting March 11, 1979 (Box 2)
      - The Black Dilemma: You Can't Lie to God March 18, 1979 (Box 2)
      - The Black Dilemma: KUA March 25, 1979 (Box 2)
      - The Black Dilemma: A New Perspective for the Black Struggle April 1, 1979 (Box 2)
      - The Black Dilemma: The Triumphal Entry April 8, 1979 (Box 2)
      - The Black Dilemma: And They Believed Them Not April 15, 1979 (Box 2)
      - The Fall of Man June 3, 1979 (Box 2)
      - Orientation Lecture June 4, 1979 (Box 2)
      - Beyond Rational Consciousness: You Need to Study KUA June 10, 1979 (Box 2)
      - Orientation Lecture June 11, 1979 (Box 2)
      - Beyond Rational Consciousness: Spiritual Encounters-You Need to Study KUA June 17, 1979 (Box 2)
      - Beyond Rational Consciousness: The Group Experience June 24, 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1981-1990
      - Surviving the 80's Through Christian Service: The Unity of Believers November 19, 1981 (Box 2)
      - Transcendence & Transformation Through the Experience of God: Is There No Balm In Gilead? April 22, 1982 (Box 2)
      - The Abundant Life: The Art of Living May 25, 1982 (Box 2)
      - God Is Power November 13, 1983 (Box 2)
      - Transforming Community: Struggle for Change #2 March 1, 1984 (Box 2)
      - Transforming Community: Genesis II -- The Recreation of Man May 6, 1984 (Box 2)
      - An Introduction to BCN Theology: Personal Change: The Key To Black Liberation August 5, 1984 (Box 2)
      - An Introduction to BCN Theology: 2nd in a Series August 12, 1984 (Box 2)
      - An Introduction to BCN Theology: The Black Man's Inner Conflicts, 3rd in A Series August 19, 1984 (Box 2)
      - The Black Nation Israel, Pt. 1 December 2, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Advent Sermon Series: The Messianic Expectations December 9, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Advent Sermon Series: The Ministry of Jesus December 16, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Advent Sermon Series: The Celebration of Christmas December 23, 1990 (Box 2)
    - 1995-1997 miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Sermons -- drafts and notes
    - Drafts
      - 1951-1953 (Box 2)
      - 1960s (Box 2)
      - Undated (Box 2)
    - Notes 1970-1983 (Box 2)
    - Rough drafts
      - 1967 (Box 2)
      - 1968 (Box 2)
      - 1960s, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - circa 1970 (Box 2)
      - 1979 (Box 2)
      - Undated (Box 2)
  - Writings
    - Black Christian Nationalism (manuscript), 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Black Messiah (manuscript), 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Nothing is More Sacred than the Liberation of the Black People (manuscript) (Box 3)
    - Poetry: Holy Crusade 1984 Words of Inspiration: Poems of Jaramogi (Box 3)
- Shrine of the Black Madonna -- Detroit
  Much of the Shrine of the Black Madonna Detroit series is comprised of an alphabetical topical file drawn together from different portions of Cleage's files and other miscellaneous church files. The series dates from the early 1950's to 2005. The bulk of the material dates from late 1960's to the mid 1970's and documents the transformation of St. Mark's to the Church of the Black Madonna and the development of the Black Christian Nationalist (BCN) denomination. The BCN files includes administrative information and documentation of the denomination's spiritual underpinnings, as presented in bible study sheets and African history lessons.
  From this series, Albert Cleage is shown to be deeply involved in both civil rights and the problems facing the city of Detroit. He served on numerous committees and commissions, ran for public office several times, and was deeply interested and involved with the Detroit Public School System, the United Church of Christ's Commission for Racial Justice, and the Interreligious Foundation for Community Organization.
  Other important files contain Sunday bulletins from church services. These are from all time periods (with the majority being either from the 1970's or the first decade of the new millennium). There is also membership information (often including addresses and family information) from the 1950's to the 1970's.
  - Bulletins of church services 1953-2007 (many gaps)
    - 1953-1969 (Box 3)
    - 1970-1973 (Box 3)
    - 1974-April 1976 (Box 3)
    - May 1976-May 1978 (Box 3)
    - 1982
      - January 1982 (Box 3)
      - February 1982 (Box 3)
      - March 1982 (Box 3)
      - April 1982 (Box 3)
      - May 1982 (Box 3)
      - June 1982 (Box 3)
      - July 1982 (Box 3)
      - August 1982 (Box 3)
      - September 1982 (Box 3)
      - October 1982 (Box 3)
      - November 1982 (Box 3)
      - December 1982 (Box 3)
    - 1980s (Box 3)
    - 1990s (Box 3)
    - 2000-2007 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Central Congregational Church Administrative
    - Articles of Association 1955 (Box 4)
    - Calendars 1960, 1961, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Executive Committee
      - 1954-1955 (Box 4)
      - 1957-1961 (Box 4)
      - 1967-1971 (Box 4)
    - Financial
      - 1957-1962 (Box 4)
      - 1963-1970 (Box 4)
    - Trustees James C. Trimble and John W. Estes, Jr. (complaint against Cleage to the Congregational Association of Detroit) 1964 (Box 4)
    - Monthly Narrative Reports 1958-1960 (Box 4)
    - Stewardship Reports (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Topical file
    - Accord, Inc. (Common Housing Corporation) 1968 (Box 4)
    - Action Council 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Action Groups 1971
      - Action Group #5 (Box 4)
      - Action Group #6 (Box 4)
    - Activity Regulations 1970-1972 (Box 4)
    - Alkebu-lan Academy and Nursery (Box 4)
    - Annual Meeting
      - 1972 (Box 4)
      - 1973 (Box 4)
    - Annual Report
      - 1953 (Box 4)
      - 1959 (Box 4)
      - 1960 (Box 4)
      - 1964 (Box 4)
      - 1966 (Box 4)
      - 1967 (Box 4)
      - 1968 (Box 4)
      - 1969 (Box 4)
      - 1970 (Box 4)
      - 1971 (Box 4)
      - 1972 (Box 4)
    - Articles of Association: Pan African Orthodox Christian Church 1978 (Box 4)
    - Ashanti Co-op/Black Star Co-op Supermarket 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Benevolent and Protective Order of the Black Madonna (Box 4)
    - Black Christian Nationalism
      - Bible Study
        - 1976 (Box 4)
        - 1997-2000 (Box 4)
      - Church Policy (Box 4)
      - College Cadre 1973 (Box 4)
      - First Annual Convention 1970 (Box 4)
      - Second Annual Convention 1971 (Box 4)
      - BCN Report to the Nation 1973 (Box 4)
      - Third Biennial Convention 1975 (Box 4)
      - History (Box 4)
      - Information Packet 1992 (Box 4)
      - Jubilee 2003 (Box 5)
      - Office and Cultural Center Management 1972 (Box 5)
      - Official Documents (Box 5)
      - Players 1972 (Box 5)
      - Poems, Songs, and Cheers (Box 5)
      - Relationship with Christian Churches 1967 (Box 5)
      - Rituals
        - Communalism Rituals 1982 (Box 5)
        - Rite of Passage (Box 5)
      - Shrine Newsletter 1970 (Box 5)
      - Student Movement 1970-1972 (Box 5)
      - Training Center and Residence Hall 1970-1975 (Box 5)
    - Black Ecumenical Council 1967, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Black Messiah Reviews 1969 (Box 5)
    - Black Manifesto -- Responses (Box 5)
    - Black Nation News 1969-1977 (Box 5)
    - Black Slate (Box 5)
    - Black Teachers Workshop (Box 5)
    - Building Fund and Relocation Committee 1955 (Box 5)
    - Camp Talahi 1959 (Box 5)
    - Catholic Clergy Conference on the Interracial Apostolate 1968 (Box 5)
    - Center City Association (Box 5)
    - Chanza (Box 5)
    - Citywide Citizen's Action Committee 1967-1968 (Box 5)
    - Commission for Racial Justice (United Church of Christ) 1969-1971 (Box 5)
    - Committees 1970s (Box 5)
    - Congregational Association of Detroit 1956 (Box 5)
    - Cooperative Services, Inc. (Box 5)
    - "Crockett Incident," 1969 (Box 5)
    - Cultural Centers (Box 5)
    - Detroit Public Library 1967 (Box 5)
    - Economic Development Corporation 1967-1969 (Box 5)
    - Education 1968 (Box 5)
    - Federation for Self Determination 1967-1968 (Box 5)
    - Flyers announcing church services
      - 1954-1960 undated (Box 5)
      - 1957-1961 (Box 5)
      - 1968-1971 (Box 5)
      - 1972-1974 (Box 5)
      - 1975 (Box 5)
      - 1976 (Box 5)
      - 1977 (Box 5)
      - 1978
        - Flyers (Box 5)
        - Drafts (Box 5)
      - January-October 1979, 10 folders (Box 5)
      - 1970s miscellaneous (Box 5)
      - April-December 1980, 9 folders (Box 5)
      - 1981, 12 folders (Box 6)
      - 1982, 12 folders (Box 6)
      - 1983, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - 1984, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - 1985-2006 (Box 6)
      - Undated, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Freedom Now Party 1964 (Box 6)
    - Funeral Obsequies (Box 6)
    - History, Draft 1968 (Box 6)
    - Illustrated News 1964 (Box 6)
    - ICOC (Box 6)
    - Inner City Mutual Insurance Company 1969 (Box 6)
    - Inner City Organizing Committee 1967-1968 (Box 6)
    - Inner City Parent's Council 1968 (Box 6)
    - Inner City Shopping Centers (Box 6)
    - Interreligious Foundation for Community Organization (IFCO) 1969, 1970 (Box 6)
    - KUA Small Group Devotionals 1992 (Box 6)
    - Layout 1972 Booklet (Box 6)
    - Locke -- The Detroit Riots of 1967 (Box 6)
    - Maccabee Training Materials undated (Box 6)
    - Marriage Rituals 1970-1974 (Box 6)
    - Mass Media Study Committee 1969 (Box 6)
    - Ministers for Racial and Social Justice 1969 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - Miss Black America Beauty Pageant 1970 (Box 6)
    - MTG (Box 6)
    - Operation Connection 1968 (Box 6)
    - Order of Nzinga (Box 6)
    - Preliminary Self Study #2 1961 (Box 6)
    - Programs and Special Events (Box 6)
    - St Mark's Presbyterian/Independent/Congregational Church 1952-1954 (Box 6)
    - Shrine #9 Internal Documents (Box 6)
    - Shrine #10, 25th Anniversary (Box 7)
    - Sudan Club 1977 (Box 7)
    - Synod 2000 (Box 7)
    - Training Group # 11 1972 (Box 7)
    - Westminster 1954 (Box 7)
    - Webster, John, Forum Committee 1969 (Box 7)
    - White Critiques 1968 (Box 7)
    - Youth
      - Youth Fellowship
        - 1954-1955 (Box 7)
        - 1956 (Box 7)
        - 1961 (Box 7)
      - Notes and Names (Box 7)
      - Youth Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Membership Information/Guest Books
    - Saint Mark's Community Church Membership Information Flyers 1951-1953 (Box 7)
      (Includes family information)
    - Every Member Canvass 1955 (Box 7)
    - Every Member Canvass 1956-1957 (Box 7)
    - Members and Guests of Central Church 1957-1959 (Box 7)
    - Members, Miscellaneous 1951-1961 (Box 7)
    - Members, Miscellaneous undated (Box 7)
    - Canvass 1963 (Box 7)
    - Membership list pre-1972 (Box 7)
    - Membership list June 1972 (Box 7)
    - Members by Geographic Location 1972 (Box 7)
    - Book of Prospective Members 1967-1969 (Box 7)
    - Names -- From Files of Kokayi Enharo undated (Box 7)
    - Pledge Cards 1967 Special Building Fund (Box 7)
    - Application for Membership 1972-1973 (Box 7)
      (not microfilmed)
    - Application for Membership 1952-1953 (Box 7)
    - Guest books
      - September 1957-January 1959 (Box 8)
      - March 1959-October 1967 (Box 8)
      - June 1969, April 1970, May-November 1972, January 1973 (Box 8)
      - May-October 1973 (Box 8)
      - October 1973-May 1974 (Box 8)
      - May 1974-January 1975 (Box 8)
- Church Leaders
  The Church Leaders series consists of files maintained by individuals, within the church who assisted Cleage in his ministry. These include Cardinal Aminifu (Woodrow Smith), Kokayi Enharo (Carl Ware), and Colonel Kwesi.
  - Cardinal Aminifu (Woodrow Smith) files
    (Cardinal Aminifu was director of the Health and Social Services Bureau, Pan-African Orthodox Christian Church)
    - Bulletins and Bible Study -- Shrine #9 (Box 8)
    - Bible Study 1978 (Box 8)
    - Roots of African History 1994 (Box 8)
    - Sermons, Shrine #9 1989-1995 (Box 8)
    - "The African Orthodox Church and Garveyism," 1971 (Box 8)
  - Kokayi Enharo (Carl Ware) files
    (Head of Maccabees)
    - BCN Songs (Box 8)
    - COR (Box 8)
    - Correspondence 1986-2003 (Box 8)
    - Clippings (Box 8)
    - Doctrine and Positions (Box 8)
    - Flyers and Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Maccabees (Box 8)
    - Obsequies and Obituaries (Box 8)
    - Security, areas of responsibility (Box 8)
    - Weekly Squad Accountability Reports (Box 8)
    - Y2K (Box 8)
    - Youth (Box 8)
  - Colonel Kwesi files
    - 1964 (Box 8)
    - 1966 (Box 8)
    - 1969 (Box 8)
- Shrines of the Black Madonna National Office (Detroit)